Date: 21-04-2011

Introduction to blogs.perl.org + Text::Table

Hello, Perl bloggers! I decided to start blogging about a most of my exclusively Perl-related stuff here on blogs.perl.org, in hope of getting more comments from active Perlers. (Until now, I've blogged about it on my technical LiveJournal blog and previously on use.perl.org Journal.). You can learn more about me on my home site - www.shlomifish.org .

OK, having put that aside - let's move on to the main topic of this post.

Many months ago I wanted to use the Text::Table CPAN module to present a table related to the meta-scan heuristics construction scheme of Freecell Solver. Now, I wanted to present nicely formatted borders, using the Unicode box-drawing characters (which some people would recall from DOS). However, I found it difficult to specify the separators in the rulers properly based on their indices - they were assumed to be the same globally. As a result, I've written a patch, and placed the modifications in a github repository.

The author of Text-Table (ANNO) told me he was working on a new version of Text-Table, which will contain many improvements. However, I was still interested in an enhanced version of the old Text-Table codebase with my patch, and after talking on #perl, ANNO said I could have co-maint on Text-Table-1.x and continue to improve it. The new Text-Table will be released under a separate namespace - Text::Table2 or so.

Many thanks go to ANNO for agreeing that I further develop Text::Table.

Using my git repository, I did many cleanups, like add pod.t and pod-coverage.t, tweak the author information, add more strict and warnings to the file, etc. ANNO 's original licence is "Same terms as Perl", but since it is an iffy licensing, I decided that all further changes will be under the terms of the Public-Domain/X11L/etc.. People who send me pull requests on github may wish to add their names to the credits (in the changes or even in the core module) but must not claim copyrights to their changes.

OK, now for some output of the Unicode table:

┌───────╥─────┬──────┬─────┬────┬──────┐
│ Place ║ 1   │ 2    │ 3   │ 4  │ 5    │
├───────╫─────┼──────┼─────┼────┼──────┤
│ 1     ║ 68  │ 317  │ 15  │ 3  │ 381  │
├───────╫─────┼──────┼─────┼────┼──────┤
│ 2     ║ 171 │ 482  │ 31  │ 14 │ 594  │
├───────╫─────┼──────┼─────┼────┼──────┤
│ 3     ║ 275 │ 867  │ 42  │ 22 │ 1007 │
├───────╫─────┼──────┼─────┼────┼──────┤
│ 4     ║ 458 │ 1442 │ 125 │ 30 │ 1630 │
├───────╫─────┼──────┼─────┼────┼──────┤
│ 5     ║ 640 │ 1715 │ 137 │ 47 │ 1730 │
└───────╨─────┴──────┴─────┴────┴──────┘

Future plans are:

Convert the remaining test scripts to Test::More.
Go over the code and clean it up
Add CPAN keywords to the META.yml. (Perhaps this will require defining a Module-Build-based Build.PL file).
Add URLs to the META.yml - to the module's homepage, to the github repository, etc..
Possibly implement some future features.
Add some more tests.

Contributions are naturally welcome, just fork the github repository and send me a pull request. (Or patches are also OK.)

Date: 20-06-2011
YAPC

Transferring a Ticket to YAPC::Europe::2011

I originally planned to attend YAPC::Europe::2011 in Riga, Latvia (on 15-17 August, 2011), and so bought an early bird ticket, but will no longer be able to attend due to personal reasons. As a result, I'm now seaking to transfer the ticket to someone else, for the right price (which will be cheaper than what I bought it.).

If you are interested, please contact me and we will negotiate a price. I hope everybody enjoys the YAPCs.

Date: 20-06-2011
XML, libxml, CPAN

Resuming Maintenance of XML-LibXML

For a long while, work on the XML-LibXML CPAN module halted as the existing maintainer was busy. After a discussion on the Perl-in-XML mailing list, some people and I were given co-maintainer status and we resumed its maintenance inside a Bitbucket.org Mercurial repository.

So far what I did, was fix some low-hanging fruit bugs, apply some patches, as well as start the long process of converting the test suite, which still uses Test.pm to Test::More . There are still many bugs lurking there, and some of them are XS bugs that are still beyond my reach, and I could use some assistance there. But it's a start.

If you're interested in helping, the clone the repository, write a patch and send me a pull request.

Text::Table Update: I've written about resuming the maintenance of Text::Table in April, and it progressed nicely: the tests were converted to Test::More, a lot of the code was cleaned up, the build system was converted to Module::Build, and keywords and resource URLs were defined, and some bugs were solved (along with tests). I'm still looking into ways to clean up the code, and if anyone has an idea for a cool feature, then they should drop me a line (or provide a patch).

Date: 23-06-2011
QA, PPI, Perl

PPI-Based Script to Convert Test.pm-based Test Programs to Test::More

Some CPAN modules I inherited used the old Test.pm for some of their t/*.t scripts instead of the more modern Test::More. This annoys me to no end because Test.pm is very limited. When I worked on Config-IniFiles, I did the conversion manually, which was a lot of work. More recently, I started working on XML-LibXML which has over 40 of those pesky Test.pm scripts, and I did not have the nerve to do all the manual and menial work.

As a result, I ended up spending a few hours studying PPI (the Perl Parsing Interface), and writing a script to automatically convert Test.pm-based scripts to Test::More. The main issue at hand was that in Test.pm, a single argument ok() tests for the scalar's truth, while a double argument ok() tests for simple equivalence (similarly to Test::More's is()). Eventually, I got the script working, with some limitations (see the page).

So what was my impression of PPI? It naturally seems more robust than using regular expressions and hacks to process Perl code, but there were a few quirks. For example, a PPI list contains an array of its contents, and the commas are part of them, as are the various other tokens in the sub-expressions. Therefore, divining the count of the arguments is pretty hard. I would have expected to get a more abstract syntax tree of the arguments, and since I didn't I had to work around it with an ugly kludge.

Furthermore, after stringifying the document object, the contents of the here-documents were not included in the output from some reason. However, I may have done something wrong. I also wish the PPI PODs contained more meaningful examples.

Nevertheless, my script is mostly working now and I can utilise it to "test-lift" legacy test programs. You might find it useful too, so it's there in case you need it, and patches to fix its limitations would be welcome.

Date: 09-11-2011
Perl, QA, XS, Inline, C, ctypes, gcc

My Experience with Inline::C

I know I didn’t write here for a long time, and I apologise for it, but I have this entry and another one in mind and I hope they can compensate for it.

For my work on Freecell Solver, I’ve written some code for encoding and decoding game positions into a compact format, by encoding them as a delta from the position of origin. I first wrote it in Perl, in order to prototype it, and later translated it to C (which is the language that Freecell Solver is written in). I have written some rudimentary unit tests for it, but also wanted to test the code against a large number of positions, by runnign it over the solutions of many Freecell deals.

The encoding rearranges the order of the card columns and the freecells, so testing that the output test is correct requires calculating that arrangement. This was also done by the Perl code. I decided to write a small wrapper for an encoding+decoding round-trip in C, and use it from a Perl program I was writing. So far so good.

I first looked at the Perl version of Ctypes, but it failed a large number of its assertions on my system, so I could not really trust it. Then I looked at Inline::C. I could not understand from its main page, how to return an SV * containing a string from it, but this was covered in the extensive Inline::C cookbook and I wrote this Inline::C function:

extern char * fc_solve_user_INTERNAL_delta_states_enc_and_dec(
    const char * init_state_str_proto,
    const char * derived_state_str_proto
    );

SV* enc_and_dec(char * init_state_s, char * derived_state_s) {
    SV * ret;
    char * s;
    s = fc_solve_user_INTERNAL_delta_states_enc_and_dec(init_state_s, derived_state_s);

    ret = newSVpv(s, 0);
    free(s);
    return ret;
}

I don't need to use “sv_2mortal” there because Inline::C does that for us. Then I tried to test it. It failed with this error:

perl: symbol lookup error: /home/shlomif/progs/freecell/trunk/fc-solve/source/_Inline/lib/auto/Mega_Test_for_C_delta_states_pl_9385/Mega_Test_for_C_delta_states_pl_9385.so: undefined symbol: fc_solve_user_INTERNAL_delta_states_enc_and_dec

I was familiar with errors like that, but it took me over an hour of playing with the various Inline::C configuration options, and trying to figure out why it didn’t link against the relevant Freecell Solver library to realise what the problem was. It was that the library in question did not export the symbol, and gcc realised it didn't give the XS extension anything and omitted it.

After fixing this line in my C source:

char * DLLEXPORT fc_solve_user_INTERNAL_delta_states_enc_and_dec(

To this line:

DLLEXPORT char * fc_solve_user_INTERNAL_delta_states_enc_and_dec(

Everything worked properly, and I was able to run the so-called “mega-test”.

If you’re having similar problems with Inline::C, you should try to add CLEAN_AFTER_BUILD => 0 to its configuration. It ended up clarifying a lot for me.

Cheers!

Date: 09-11-2011
exec, perl, portability, whitespace, windows, unix

exec's portability

Pop quiz! What does this perl 5 program prints when executed with no arguments?

#!/usr/bin/perl

use strict;
use warnings;

if (! @ARGV)
{
    exec($^X, $0, "hello world");
}
else
{
    my $arg = shift(@ARGV);
    print "Got <$arg>\n";
    if (@ARGV)
    {
        print "Other args are <@ARGV>\n";
    }
}

The answer is “it depends.”. On my Linux system it prints “Got <hello world>”, while on Windows, using Strawberry Perl, it prints “Got <hello>” and later on that the other args are “world”.

I would expect the Linux behaviour were every argument passed to the list exec arrives as one argument to @ARGV regardless of whitespace as the correct. It also the behaviour exhibited on both operating systems using system. Is this a bug?

perlport only has this to say about whitespace: Whitespace in filenames is tolerated on most systems, but not all, and even on systems where it might be tolerated, some utilities might become confused by such whitespace..

I discovered this strange mis-behaviour when working on a commission for a client who is Windows-based.

Date: 03-12-2011
Perl, Mongers, Tel Aviv, Israel, meeting, DBI, DBIx-Class, local-lib, perlbrew, cpanminus, CPAN, Firebird, SQL

Report on the Latest Tel Aviv Perl Mongers Meeting

I attended the latest Tel Aviv Perl Mongers (TelAviv.pm) meeting the other day, and am writing this report in order to encourage more people to come. We didn't have meetings in September or October due to the Jewish holidays and some renovations on the site, so it was good to finally have a meeting.

Before the meeting, I had helped publicise it on various online news channels, and thankfully quite a few people (about 20-30) came. I had a previous appointment that day at 12:00, and so returned home where I ate, worked on the computer, and rested before the TelAviv.pm meeting.

After I rode the bus, I arrived there a few minutes earlier. I met a fellow Perl monger on the way. We found the room with some difficulty, as there were very few signs outside the doors of the various rooms in the building. Several people including Gabor were already sitting in the room. They were discussing the upcoming Israeli Perl Workshop in February. In any case, I decided to walk to the nearby grocery store to buy some refreshments for the meeting, and when I returned there were more people in the room.

Quite a few people arrived relatively late, but the talks started mostly on schedule. The first talk (by Erez Schatz) was short, and it discussed some recent tools that facilitate the Perl programmer’s life: local-lib, perlbrew, cpanm and pm-uninstall. The talk was very fun, and he ended up covering some other tools in brief in the last slide. I’m still not convinced that I should use CPAN-Minus instead of my CPANPLUS (especially given CPANPLUS-Dist-Mageia and friends), but I still like perlbrew and local::lib and pm-uninstall seems useful.

Erez mentioned that on Perl forums there were several very common and hated questions like “How do I uninstall a perl module?” or “How can I use CPAN without root?” and that these technologies address these needs precisely.

After this talk, Erez gave a longer talk about DBIx-Class, which is an Object-Relational Mapper (ORM) for Perl. For the demo, he used a company whose employees are dogs, and the slides featured many pictures of dogs in suits (some of them pretty scary). There were a few glitches in the demonstration, but they were promptly overcome, and the DBIC_TRACE=1 flag was a big help. One bug in the code was that instead of updating the employee's department (by looking it up by name), the department's name was updated (globally). I any case, it was an enjoyable talk, but the person who sat next to me said that she didn’t like it because she used to be a DBA, and she was worried about performance.

Erez mentioned that DBIx-Class was the “Elephant in the Room” of Perl ORMs, which I had concluded was the case as well.

After that talk, there was a break, where people got to eat more of the cookies I bought and to chat. Afterwards, Ido Kanner presented about Firebird SQL. It was a good talk, and Ido drew some comparisons between Firebird and SQLite, MySQL and PostgreSQL. Firebird looks interesting and it also has embedded (like SQLite) and read-only modes.

One problem during the talk was that the projector kept shutting down, and it took us some trouble to restart it. We hoped this problem would be resolved in upcoming meetings.

After the meeting, some of us (about 10) went to Spaghettim (a pasta/etc. place) and had dinner. We chatted about Atheism, Cable company tech-support, GNOME 3 and KDE 4, and lots of other stuff. This time I had a pizza, which although not too bad, made me realise I will be ordering pasta there from now on.

To sum up, it was a very enjoyable meeting, and I’m looking forward for more future ones. One thing notable about it is that this time Sawyer did not deliver a talk, which made him happy because other people volunteered to do so instead.

Date: 26-12-2011
perl,debugger,debugging,refactoring,features,sopa,telaviv,mongers

Breaking the Perl Debugger for Fun and Profit

Before I cover the main topic of this entry, here are some short news and action items:

If you have not acted against SOPA - the proposed online blacklist/censorship bill, you should. Follow the link for information on how to act against it.

I have announced the next Tel Aviv Perl Mongers meeting on my technical journal on LiveJournal.com. It will take place this Wednesday, on 28 December, 2011. More information in the link.

Anarchy Golf is a new server for Code Golf, which are online programming competitions for implementing code as shortly as possible. It supports Perl 5, Perl 6 and many other languages. There is an active challenge, where the only Perl 5 submission so far is mine, so I could use some competition.

Now for the main topic of the post. Recently, three patches were integrated into the perl-5 core implementing new features in the perl debugger:

Add "b <filename>:<line> <cond>" to perl -d by me.
Add enable/disable commands for breakpoints in perl -d also by me.
"Trace to max depth" by Peter Scott.

When Father Chrysostomos tried to apply the first patch, he noticed its tests started failing. Apparently, the breakpoint functionality (irrespective of the patch's added functionality) became broken in bleadperl, due to a change in the internals, and it wasn't caught by the debugger's existing tests. I ended up submitting another patch to add a test for some of the existing breakpoint functionality.

The other two patches passed all of their own tests and the existing ones, but that wasn't the end of the story. A short time afterwards a regression was reported in the debugger, which was caused by one of the patches that I introduced. While, I fixed it with a test, it was soon followed by other reports and fixes. None of these bugs were caught by the test suite of the perl debugger, which is incredibly incomplete.

Another E-mail that caused an active discussion was my proposal to add strict and warnings to lib/perl5db.pl, in which someone kept arguing against it, and eventually said he confused it (it being the defualt command-line debugger front-end) with the debugger's guts, and ended up also supporting adding "use strict;".

I ended up working on adding "strict" to the debugger on a git branch, and was eventually successful (though I temporarily broken no-strict code on the debugger evaluated lines, to which I added a test.). RJBS (the current pumpking) said he'd like to integrate this patch only after perl-5.16.x is released.

The morals of this story is that the perl debugger needs more tests, and that trying to enhance it can easily break it. I started a branch on GitHub where I've been committing more tests to the perl debugger to enhance its coverage.

There's also a Google Code-In task for devising a strategy to do that, and I've volunteered to mentor it. All this will hopefully result in less breakage in the future.

Happy Holidays, and a Happy New Year.

Date: 27-03-2012
perl, workshop, israel, events, 2012

Report on the Israeli Perl Workshop 2012

Well, I've got a lot of stuff I’d like to blog about in the various blogs of mine, and so I’m starting with this report on the Israeli Perl Workshop of 2012, which had taken place in 28 February, 2012. Moreover, April Fools' Day is approaching, and I had an idea for a Perl-related April Fools' gag, but after telling it to RJBS (the current Perl pumpking), he and I agreed that it would hit too many nerves. (PerlJam on IRC said he liked it, though). Maybe I’ll publish it on 2 April with a big disclaimer on top, just for kicks.

Anyway, here is the report. I had originally posted it to the Perl in Israel mailing list for review, but did not get any reviews, so it may not be too letter-perfect, but I guess that’s life.

This is my report about the Israeli Perl Workshop of 2012 . It was a fun and educational event, and I'm glad I was able to attend it. For better or for worse, all the talks I attended were in Room 1, but I was still able to hear the ends of a few talks in Room 2 (because the corresponding talks in Room 1 ended before them).

I set up an alarm the night before in order to wake up early in time for the event, and ended up waking up some time before it (and even the alarm time was much earlier than what I was used to). Then I made some preparations, ate breakfast, and caught the appropriate bus. After I walked from the bus station to Shenkar, it took me some time to find the place, because it wasn't the same entrance as our normal rooms, and the signs were confusing. What I needed to do was to take the stairs down to the yard, and then go to the organisation room, but it was hard to find.

There I got my name sticker, the schedule, and some swag from booking.com. I’d like to thank Booking.com for sponsoring the Israeli Perl Workshop 2012 (as well as having a presence there and giving some swag and chocolates), and they are looking for software developers with Perl experience to relocate to Amsterdam, so please consider working for them.

In the yard, I met a few people including Florian Ragwitz (a.k.a "FLORA" on CPAN or "rafl" on IRC - he has many cool modules there, including quite a few XS ones), who was one of the workshop’s visitors from Germany. Despite being German, his English accent sounded English to us. Later on we discussed accents in English and he noted that the accents of some Israelis he met sounded like French to him (while ours seemed less so). This is strange, because Israelis can distinguish between a French accent in English and an Israeli Hebrew accent in English.

Anyway, Florian told me that he is planning on reviewing and pulling my Test::Aggregate GitHub pull request Real Soon Now™, a fact which has brought me some relief, because I've tried to contact him on IRC and ask him if he remembers.

For better or for worse, all the talks that I preferred to hear took place in room #1 (while sometimes visiting Room #2) to hear the ends of talks. I still would be happy to hear many of the talks that took place in Room #2 in the normal Tel Aviv Perl Mongers meetings, or alternatively, those talks in room #1 which lacked enough time to be conveyed satisfactorily.

The first talk in the day was Ran Eilam’s talk about "Syntactic Sugar causes Cancer of the Semicolon”, which had to be trimmed towards the end, because the introduction may have taken too long. The talk was interesting starting from an example of ptr->val being sugar in the C programming language for (*ptr).val and continuing to further examples. Ran raised the issue of whether syntactic sugar was important or not, which turns out to not be a straightforward question. He then demonstrated some modules for syntactic sugar on CPAN.

I hope Ran can give a rerun of it on one of the mongers' meetings with more time allocated for that.

After that I attended the talk of Stefan Hornburg (“racke”, known as HORNBURG on CPAN) who was another visitor from Germany, about Template::Flute which is a designer’s friendly template system. In this template, one uses an HTML file with standard HTML attributes for designating the fields that needs to be replaced, and then an XML specification file that specifies how to process the HTML (and in addition one uses Perl to give it data). As a result the designers can manipulate the HTML with their own tools, while still allowing the programmers to populate it with data.

This seems like an interesting and potentially useful tool, but it’s less expressive than template systems such as Template Toolkit. After the talk, another attendee whom we talked in private questioned the need for both the HTML file and the XML specification, but I didn't find a way to avoid it given the constraints that the HTML will be valid HTML 4/XHTML 1.

The next talk about Time Management in Software Projects was cancelled because the presenter did not come (due to lack of time management as we joked then). I was able to catch a glimpse of the end of Dotan Dimet’s “Perl and JavaScript: bioinformatics in a browser window” talk, but I don’t remember a lot of it except for a small amount of demonstration.

The talk about Zero to CPAN was eventually given by Sawyer instead of by Erez Schatz. It was a nice one, and I’ve learned about the CPAN-Changes module there (after Florian mentioned it, though). Sawyer covered the way to get to a working CPAN-like distribution from scratch using tools such as module-starter and explained what every file in the CPAN module hierarchy does, and demonstrated some test-driven-development. I knew most of it already, but it was still a fun talk.

Amir Friedman‘s talk about software configuration management (SCM) came next, and he discussed some open-source solutions for the various parts of SCM, which include version control, release management, task management, and project management. He recommended Gitflow (which we had a talk about on the Tel Aviv mongers mailing list) for version control and release management, and a different solution called Jenkins for issue tracking (if I remember correctly). I then asked what he thought of integrated “all-in-one” solutions for SCM, and he said that those were pricey and he did not have any significant experience with them.

The lunch break came next and I overheard a talk between two other people about teaching English to speakers of non-English languages. One of them said that he once worked with some Spanish Electrical Engineers and that they were “completely isolated” from the rest of the world because they didn’t read the literature in English. Then we discussed whether it was economical to teach English to hundreds of millions of speakers of Spanish, or whether we should expect most things to be translated. It was compared to the “give a man a fish” vs. “teach a man to fish”. We also discussed the fact that Dutchmen tended to have very good English, and one of the other people commented that it was true, but that they still tended to prefer using software with Dutch localisation.

I’ve also talked with Sawyer about his upcoming “CGI.pm MUST DIE!” talk. He said that he needs to become mentally energised for that talk because he feels strongly about it and wants to convey the energy. He passed an anecdote from a conference in Europe, in which he had given a talk about Dancer, and said he was so emotional then that people said “You must see him” and rushed to see his other talk. Moreover, afterwards, when asked who were the two best presenters in the conference, they said “[Someone very famous] and that Dancer guy”.

The anti-CGI.pm presenting was indeed energetic and emotional, but kinda fell below my expectations due to the yard talk that preceded it. It was still pretty informative. Dotan Dimet later took the stage for the rebuttal of “CGI.pm - the only web development framework you’ll ever need” which was less emotional but still interesting. I was not convinced that CGI.pm’s HTML generation routines were a good way to do output HTML (I never really liked them), so I may have been more convinced by Sawyer.

Ynon Perek’s talk about “Implementing Perl (Moose) Design Patterns” came next, which was interesting, but again lacked adequate time to cover everything, and I hope will be given with less time constraints. One anecdote from there was that Ynon said there where three primary ways for polymorphism in Perl: Inheritance (“is-a”), Roles/Traits (“does-a”) and Containment/Delegation (“has-a”) and that he could no longer recommend inheritance (but did not get to explain why not from what I recall).

In any case, I was surprised at Ynon’s implementation of the Factory pattern, and don’t remember the implementation given by him.

Next came Tamir Lousky’s talk about generating vector graphics with Perl and SVG. Its slides contained a lot of very nice eye candy. The introduction to SVG and generating it was quite rudimentary, and did not cover the full potential of SVG. The demonstration and explanation of the module for generating random trees using SVG was interesting.

David Tabachnikov’s next gave an interesting talk called “Scaling Up”. He contrasted optimisation (which makes your code run faster with the existing resources) to vertical scaling (= buying faster computers) to Horizontal scaling (= buying more hardware). He also noted that there’s some speed difference between the various SQL databases, but he did not encounter a situation where it would have made too much difference.

The last feature of the evening were the lightning talks. I recall a talk by Florian Ragwitz about Google Code-In and Google Summer-of-Code. I also recall Gabor’s talk about surviving in an uncooperative workplace. He said that if the workplace does not practise best practices such as using version control systems or writing automated tests, one can create their own small island of sanity where they make use of that on their own, and gradually convince the rest of the organisation that it’s beneficial.

After the lightning talks, some people went to a local restaurant for dinner, but I decided against it because I was too tired from waking up early. As a result, I found someone who drove up north to drive me home, and got home.

In the schedule I noticed that one could go to a certain URL at O’Reilly and receive a free E-book of their choice. I used this opportunity to get the book Beautiful Code , which I have started reading.

The day was exhausting but very fun, and I enjoyed all the talks I attended. I’d like to thank the organisers of the event and most notably Gabor Szabo and Sawyer X, Shenkar college for providing the venue, Booking.com for the sponsorship, O’Reilly for the free book presents, the foreign guests who came to present and to attend, and all the other presenters, who volunteered to give talks.

I hope we can repeat this the next year.

Date: 09-04-2012
perl, april fools, joke

The Perl April Fools' Gag That Could Have Been

On my last entry, I told you that I have had an idea for a Perl-related April Fools’ day gag, and that I would possibly reveal it on 2-April with a big disclaimer on top, just for kicks. Well, it’s already 9-April, but I guess it is better late than never, right?

OK, here is the big disclaimer: THIS IS A JOKE. IT’S NOT SERIOUS. SO RELAX - IT IS NOT GOING TO HAPPEN SOON (AND HOPEFULLY WILL NOT EVER HAPPEN)..

OK, now let’s move on to the gag itself:

1 April 2012, Tel Aviv, Israel: the Perl foundation has announced today that by inspiration from Mozilla Firefox, the perl-porters (formerly known as perl5-porters) will adopt a schedule of a quarterly major release.

“Since version 6 of Perl has been claimed by a malevolent project that amounted to very little, we will release Perl version 7 next Summer, followed by Perl 8 in next Fall, and Perl 9 next Winter.” said the designated Perl pumpking.The Perl foundation commented that it is sure that users will appreciate the accelerated release schedule, despite the fact that a lot of backwards’ compatibility will be broken in each release to further the language’s improvement.

Some prominent Perl porters have added that they are looking into ways to automatically upgrade the Perl version automatically upon new releases, similar to the approach followed by the Google Chrome browser. “We are tired of people using outdated versions of Perl, which results in a maintenance burden for us, to say nothing of the security risk by bugs in old Perl versions. So we think the best way to mitigate that would be to simply force people to upgrade.”

The Perl porters are hard at work on perl-7.0.0, which will implement the upcoming Perl 7 specification with many new and exciting features and incompatibilities.

Well, like I said, after discussing this idea with RJBS (the current Perl 5 Pumpking), he and I agreed that it would be too cruel, given that many people are sensitive about upgrading their versions of Perl 5. Comparisons of how old the perl that your workplace/client/etc. has deployed on their systems is a common source of discussion among perl mongers (and someone told me one of his clients still used perl 4), and many people would have found such an announcement alarming instead of funny. But I hope you enjoyed reading it, and hope you're also looking forward to perl-5.16.0, which should be out soon.

Date: 09-07-2012
perl, begin, beginners, perl-begin, learn

What’s new on the Perl Beginners’s Site

The last update on the news feed for The Perl Beginners’s site was almost a year ago. While the site continued to improve, I neglected writing a new entry until now, so I hope this one will compensate for that.

So without further ado, here is what is new:

We now have a page about Perl Humour, which was restored from a page in the now offline perl.net.au wiki.

Also originally from that wiki is the Freenode’s #perl channel Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ) List, which is well worth a read.

Another restored page is the list of CPAN Wrappers for Distributions.

We added a page about web automation in Perl, and one about manipulating files and directories.

The Perl on Windows page was enhanced with new links to Strawberry Perl and DWIM Perl.

We have a new page about Perl Training Providers, which currently only contains a link to the Perl Training Directory.

The “Perl Elements to Avoid” page contains many new entries.

Our mirror of the book Modern Perl by chromatic was updated to its latest edition.

We hope you find these additions useful or enlightening.

Date: 22-07-2012
perl, cpan, dancer

Announcement: the App-Notifier CPAN Distributions

I would like to announce two new CPAN distributions of mine: App-Notifier-Service and App-Notifier-Client. These are derived from a few simplistic scripts I've written in shell and Perl, to allow me to notify when a task has finished (e.g: make ; finish-client) or a certain time has elapsed (e.g: sleep 240 ; finish-client), and I decided to create something more serious as CPAN modules.

App-Notifier-Service implements an HTTP service (using Dancer), which listens for requests, and once one arrives, implements a callback, which notifies the user on the localhost that the event occured. App-Notifier-Client complements it by implementing a client that connects to the service and sends the event.

Currently documentation may be lacking, and there are almost no automated tests in the distributions, but it appears to work nicely. To get started, read the documentation and you may wish to peruse some of these files from my home directory. First of all, the .app_notifier.yml file:

commands:
    default:
        - /home/shlomif/bin/desktop-finish-cue
    cookie:
        - /home/shlomif/bin/desktop-finish-cue
        - "--song"
        - "/home/music/Music/dosd-mp3s/Cookie.mp3"
client:
    targets:
        default:
            url: "http://localhost:6300/"
        lap:
            url: "http://lap.shlomifish.org:6300/"

The desktop-finish-cue file:

#!/bin/bash

song="/home/music/Music/dosd-mp3s/Theme - Eurovision.mp2"

param="$1"
shift
if test "$param" = "--song"; then
    arg="$1"
    shift
    song="$arg"
fi

xmessage "Your task has been finished! Go check it out." &
mplayer "$song"

And the finish-server script:

#!/bin/bash
cd "$HOME"/progs/perl/alert/http-based/hg/App-Notifier-Service &&
    perl ./bin/app.pl --port=6300

Otherwise, if you're in the Tel Aviv or vicinity, you are invited to the next Tel Aviv Perl Mongers meeting on Wednesday, 25 July 2012. Otherwise, I wish to note that I have written my first Java golf program as part of Anarchy golf’s “Alphabet Texture” challenge (Anarchy golf accepts challenges in many languages). At 167 bytes, it is over 3 times longer than the shortest Perl entry which is only 50 bytes (my Perl solution is 52 bytes). But it was fun to write. For your information, code golf is a challenge in which, participating programmers are challenged to write the shortest program that achieves a certain objective. I find it fun and addictive.

Date: 16-08-2012
perl, cpan, tip, tech, tech tip, mageia, linux

Tech Tip: How to Package and Maintain CPAN Distributions in Mageia

Mageia Linux is an RPM-based Linux distribution, whose repositories contain over 3,000 CPAN packages, and part of the reason why it has so many is because Jerome Quelin and the other maintainers have worked on tools to facilitate creating Mageia packages for CPAN distributions and maintaining them.

However, I was a little confused about using magpie, so I'd like to share my findings here:

In order to import, upload and submit a new CPAN package into Mageia, along with all of its dependencies, one should not use magpie, but rather cpan2pkg. Its use is very simple: make rpm and urpmi sudoable, and type cpan2pkg Package::Name from the command-line inside an X terminal. This will start a Tk window where one can monitor the progress of preparing new RPM packages and it has an entry box to create more packages (which saves time on re-initialising CPAN.pm or CPANPLUS.pm).

In order to upgrade a package, one can type eval $( magpie co -s perl-[PACKAGE_NAME] ) and then magpie update. magpie requires minicpan to be installed and updated.

In order to install packages, one can do sudo urpmi 'perl(Package::Name)'. My Module-Format module facilitates the translation from other notations for writing modules:

up()
{
    sudo urpmi --auto $(perlmf as_rpm_colon "$@")
}

Date: 01-09-2012
perl, foundation, tpf, grant, debugger, cpan, ruby

Grant for Improving the Perl Debugger + New CPAN Distributions

First of all, I am glad to announce that the Perl Foundation grant committee has accepted my grant proposal for adding tests and refactoring the built-in perl debugger. Here is the announcement for which grant proposals were accepted. My grant manager for this grant is Alan Haggai Alavi, whom I've been talking with online and have collaborated on a few projects, so I'm really happy to work with him again.

I have already made some progress with the grant (and this post is part of it), and sent a log for Alan Haggai to post as a grant update.

That put aside, I'd now like to publicise some of the new distributions I have uploaded to CPAN, as I had some ideas for new ones, and am also contemplating making enough uploads to have 100 CPAN distributions or more:

WWW-LinkChecker-Internal is a distribution wrapping a script that checks for internal broken links. I released the first three versions of it in a day, and it uses WWW::Mechanize. The reason why I wrote it was that the WDG HTML validator reported some broken links in one of my sites, but not their origins, so I had to trace them in a different way, and ended up writing that.

Inline-Ruby is an Inline:: distribution I adopted that allows to embed Ruby code inside Perl programs. I applied some fixes for it (some of which were not released to CPAN yet and some are ugly workarounds), and am planning to maintain it further down the road.

Test-TrailingSpace is a Test:: namespace distribution for verifying that your code does not contain trailing space. Death to trailing space!

A final anecdote is that when working on one of my CPAN modules I found the b [filename]:[line_num] feature that I implemented in the perl debugger to be of great help, and can be content that I'm eating my own dogfood.

Cheers for now.

Date: 09-09-2012
tech, tip, tech tip, perl, eumm, compiler, gcc, clang

Tech Tip: Overriding the C compiler with ExtUtils::MakeMaker

In order to override the C compiler with ExtUtils::MakeMaker, one can do something like:

perl Makefile.PL CC=/usr/bin/clang

Which will make the "CC" variable in the generated makefile be set to /usr/bin/clang instead of the default. Apparently, setting the CC environment variable does not work like it does with CMake.

Thanks to Sisyphus for the tip.

Date: 18-10-2012
lwn, lwn.net, events, perl, conferences, yapc

Please Publish Perl Events on the LWN.net Calendar

As I read last week’s LWN.net’s Announcement Page (LWN.net is a news site for open-source-related news, formerly standing for “Linux Weekly News”), I noticed that there were few if any Perl events featured in its upcoming events calendar. However, these events appear in the Perl Weekly, and there are many upcoming Python events featured in LWN.net.

So, please, if you are organising a Perl-related event (or any other major open-source event), make sure you put it on the LWN.net calendar.

Date: 14-11-2012
cpan, perl, command, line, cli, bash, gnu, parallel, sleep

Three Command-Line Utilities

So, November is NaNoWriMo (“National Novel Writing Month”), and I was hoping to get some serious writing done (instead of coding), but I kept being distracted with coding and random writing in various Internet forums. Well, hopefully this blog post will compensate a little for that.

In this post, I’d like to cover three command-line utilities - two of them new and were written by me, and one of them somewhat older, but also written in Perl.

The first utility is GNU Parallel, which allows one to run several command-line jobs in parallel, using forking and/or ssh remote logins. I used it to speed up some processing I've been doing on my computer. For more information and some examples of usage, see my post about it to the linux-elitists mailing list, and also read Thomas Sattler’s response which provides some further insights.

The second utility is countdown, which is similar to the UNIX command-line sleep command, but displays the remaining time on the console. I wrote a prototype for it in Perl 6, only to discover it consumed far too many resources. The second prototype, as a Perl 5 program consumed close to zero resources of my computer. Yesterday, I converted it to a modulino (a Perl application implemented as a module) and uploaded several versions to the CPAN.

The third utility is something I have placed in my ~/.bashrc file in order to implement reminders when the shell starts. The code for it is:

reminder_file="$HOME/.local/share/shlomif/reminder/reminder.txt"
if [ -s "$reminder_file" ] ; then
    perl -Mstrict -Mwarnings -MTerm::ANSIColor -E 'my $x = colored("===", "bold red"); say "$x Reminders $x"'
    cat "$reminder_file"
fi

Cancel_reminder()
{
    rm "$reminder_file"
}

I wrote it because I wasn't prompted in time by Thunderbird+Lightning due to a strange bug, and because I had to ditch KOrganizer because it consumed too many resources here. This displays the Reminders whenever you start a new shell, which happens quite often with me, so it's OK. I use cron jobs to append stuff into "$reminder_file", and the Perl code displays a header in colour.

That’s it for today. App-Countdown is one step closer for the count-up (pun intended) towards the coveted 100 distributions under “SHLOMIF” on CPAN, so that's another plus.

Date: 06-12-2012
cpan, perl, sdlx, xml

Count-up to 100 CPAN Distributions: Test-XML-Ordered, and SDLx-Betweener and more

Well, it's no longer a secret that I’m craving to join the “100 CPAN Distributions Club” by releasing some code that is hopefully not too useless. Here I would like to blog about the two new additions to my CPAN page which are the 83rd and 84th distributions respectively. The story is a bit more complicated than that.

The first upload is SDLx-Betweener, which allows for creating high-performance and smooth animations in SDL by making use of Perl/XS. Almost all of the coding (and a related YAPC::Israel talk) was done by Ran Eilam, who is a very cool guy, a good friend and a former boss of mine, and I've just done (with his permission) some last-minute cleanups and did the initial upload to CPAN. So I kinda feel like the frog that sat on top of the elephant who crossed the river and said “We did it!”.

However, I needed SDLx::Betweener for something I've been intending to work on, and wanted it on CPAN and packaged in Mageia Linux, so I did that. If you run into any problems with it, drop me a note or file a bug report, and hopefully I can resolve these problems (possibly with some help from Ran).

The next distribution is original, but its story is more complicated. It all started when I decided to resume work on Qantor, which aims to eventually be a modern and saner alternative to TeX/LaTeX and Troff (although it is still extremely far from that now). I noticed that the parsing was still done by Regexp::Grammars, and so decided to convert it into Parser::MGC. Parser::MGC worked eventually and I was impressed from the straightforward way to do stuff with it, but it was time consuming to get there (like most other parser generators I tried, only a bit better), and involved writing some Moose 'around' code to debug the method calls, and also sometimes delving into the code. Parser::MGC is still not perfect (and some of the code I read there had gems like die $e if $committed or not eval { $e->isa( "Parser::MGC::Failure" ) }; which I found hard to parse, and made me want to drown a kitten), but I think it sucks less and is more transparent than other parser generators I tried.

Anyway, after I got it working, I noticed that the Test::XML::Ordered code (then still unreleased), generated a some memory problems and I suspected either XML::LibXML or libxml2 to be the culprit. This involved a long investigation process with valgrind, gdb, perl -d and other tools which culminated in a very small change and more lines of test code. This was released in XML::LibXML. After that I received a report that the tests got stuck, but that turned out to be due to external loading of DTDs and was easily fixed. There's another report for a problem with perl-5.8.8 (ouch!) on Red Hat Enterprise Linux (ouch again!), but I'm not too motivated to do a lot about it (see this fortune cookie).

Well, after I fixed the problem with XML::LibXML, I decided to release Test::XML::Ordered. I'm well aware of Test::XML, but found it hard to rely on it, because it uses XML::SemanticDiff (the latter I adopted) and which attempts to rearrange the order of the nodes when it sees fit (so <ul><li>One</li><li>Two</li></ul> and <ul><li>Two</li><li>One</li></ul> may be considered the same), which was not what I want and not what other people who contacted me about XML::SemanticDiff wanted.

After Test::XML::Ordered, I decided it would be a good idea to finally work on the release of XML::GrammarBase which aims to provide “base classes and roles” for facilitating creating XML validators and processors. Work on it was pretty straightforward after I had Test::XML::Ordered available, but required some refactoring the classes from using Any::Moose to using Moo per advice of the people on #moose, and I have yet to convert the XSLT role into a parameterised role.

I have some other code I'd like to release on CPAN after all that.

Another related hacktivity was a set of patches to the core Vim that I've written to improve support for DocBook 5. Since I wanted to maintain compatibility with DocBook 4 documents (because DocBook 4 is still popular), this involved writing a Perl, Bash and Python Amalgam to generate the Vim code in question with a list of common, DocBook 4-only and DocBook 5-only tags. You an find it in its BitBucket repository and is very hacky, but it works. Using the Python code gave me an idea for a missing XML::LibXML feature - DTD introspection - which I'd like to implement in the future.

Well, that's all for now - just wanted to get it out of my system. Cheers!